A Guide to the Papers of the Davis Family 1852-1937
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Davis Family 1852-1937
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11386
ca. 450 items
There are ca. 450 items, 1852-1937, pertaining to the Davis Family, founders of the Southern Female College in Petersburg, Virginia. There is correspondence of the Davis family; and, there are correspondence, papers, photographs, and printed relating to the Southern Female College and Petersburg Female College.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the Library from Heartwood Books, Charlottesville, Virginia, on February 24, 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
Arthur Kyle Davis (1867-1953) was the son of Williams Thomas and Caroline Virginia (Robinson) Davis. He received degrees from Randolph-Macon College and Hampden-Sydney College. He married Lucy Pryor McIlwaine on November 12, 1890, and had issue: Lucy McIlwaine (Mrs. Jones), Caroline Robinson (Mrs. John B. Young), and, Arthur Kyle, Jr., President of Southern College (Junior), 1889-1942. Davis was president of the Virginia Association of Colleges and Schools for Girls and member of various associations, including the Virginia Historical Society and the Southern Association of Colleges. He was also the author of several educational and historical pamphlets.
Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. (1897-1972) was the son of Arthur Kyle and Lucy Pryor (McIlwaine) Davis. He received a bachelor degree from the University of Virginia and diplomas in economics and political science from Balliol College, Oxford. He was an instructor in English at the University of Virginia, 1923-1924, assistant professor, 1924-1927, associate professor, 1927-1940, and professor, beginning 1940. He was also a visiting professor at Harvard University, 1926, and Sweet Briar College, 1926-1927. Memberships included Modern Language Association of America, College English Association, American Folklore Society, Southeastern Folklore Society, and Phi Beta Kappa. Awards and honors included Rhodes scholar, 1920-1923; Sterling Research Fellow, Yale University, 1928-1929; and, American Council of Learned Societies grant to study Virginia folk songs, 1932. During 1918-1919, Davis served as second lieutenant in the United States Army; and, became lieutenant commander in the United States Naval Reserve, 1943-1945. Writings include: Traditional Ballads of Virginia, Folk-Songs of Virginia, and More Traditional Ballads of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Papers of Arthur Kyle Davis include correspondence of Joseph Dupuy Eggleston (1867-1953) and Reaumur Coleman Stearnes (1866-1953) relating to the State Department of Public Instruction. There is also a letter, October 16, 1913, from "Will" Davis, Atlanta Coast Line Railroad Company, Savannah, Georgia, concerning his territory and settling in a boarding place. On September 12, n.y., architect John Kevan Peebles (1876- 1934) writes that he will arrive on the Cannonball train and will proceed directly to the church. Other items of interest include a 1912 pamphlet, "Three Centuries of an Old Virginia Town..." by Davis, President of Southern Female College; vehicle permit and registration, 1913; and, two State Real Estate trust deed notes, 1920.
Papers of Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. include report cards, 1913, from the Tome School for Boys, Port Deposit, Maryland, and a letter, September 12, 1913, from Robert W[illiamson] Tunstall (1851-1917), Classical Department, Tome School, to Davis' father, discussing his credits and examination grades. There is a letter, September 30, 1920, from Davis, Jr. at Balliol College, Oxford, to his mother, Lucy Pryor (McIlwaine) Davis, discussing his experiences upon arrival in Oxford; visiting Balliol; meeting the master; the atmosphere at the college; Rhodes scholars from Oregon, Tennessee, and Nebraska; arranging a tennis game on the Balliol courts; descriptions of Balliol and the college at Oxford; a diagram and discription of his rooms at the college; a visit to Christ Church; and, his planned studies in English. Another letter, November 5, 1922, from Balliol, refers to having tea with Mr. and Mrs. (Catherine Scott) Ridley near Boar's Hill; an anecdote about the consequences of walking a Miss Northrop back to Lady Margaret Hall in the rain; Fitzgerald Flournoy, the new Virginia Rhodes scholar; a debate on the study of literature and philosophy with [Robert Kent] Gooch (1893- ); a meeting of the International Assembly, where the near-Eastern question was discussed; Theodore Marberg, once Minister to Belgium, speaking on the League of Nations at the American Club; hearing Ruth Draper (1884-1956) in a series of character sketches; and, social activities. Another letter, December 16, 1922, from Shakespeare Hotel, Stratford-on-Avon, mentions the engagement of Marjorie Hillyer to Arthur Patterson Marshall; a concert given by the Hillyers in the music room of Hall's Croft; being taken with Miss Betty Melhirst, a beautiful soprano and dancer; plans to be in London, staying at a house occupied entirely by literary and artistic people; receiving a letter from the Vice-Chancellor of Oxford about his communication on the difficulties of post-graduate work at Oxford; a visit to Shakespeare's birthplace; and, Baconian theory not existing for Stratfordians.
Papers of Williams Thomas and Caroline Virginia (Robinson) Davis include letters from their daughter, E. T. C., and son, R. B., among others. During July - August 1866, E. T. C. writes from various places, including Silva Sonora, Mecklenburg, and Pilgrim's Rest, concerning her vacation; attending a protracted meeting conducted by Mr. Blincoe; attending the Baptist Association; girls attending the next session of [Petersburg Female College]; a tournament given in honor of the Petersburg girls and the disapproval of the preachers; the "Kissing Club"; sending catalogues to certain prospective students; and, trying to recruit students for Petersburg Female College but having difficulty because of hard times for farmers. There is a letter, July 23, 1866, from R. B. Davis in Cabin Ford, concerning his trip by boat; visiting family; negative opinion of a New England school marm, Miss Harwood; crops of wheat, oats and corn; and, his father's activities in Charlottesville and Norfolk.
Other letters to Williams Thomas and Caroline Virginia (Robinson) Davis include a letter, October 27, 1867, from Agnes I. Duval in Floral Bank, British Honduras, describing her new life and the plans for same. She mentions Mr. Duval and R. F. Ledbetter having plans to have a steamboat on the river; wishing that Miss Lacy could come and be a teacher to her children climate permitting; and, having her guitar sent as she sold her piano in Mexico. A January 7, 1874 letter to "Carrie" concerns financial matters; the return of James Carroll from New Orleans; taking time to love and enjoy her children; worry over "Tom" who has been exhibiting the same symptoms of coughing and bronchitis as when at Randolph-Macon College; family news; and, the death of sister "Eliza." A February 4, 1875 letter to "Carrie" concerns a financial matter involving articles bought for Mary and Jennie; the practicality of getting a set of lower teeth; James [Carroll] not returning to his family; the improvement in Tom's health; hard times in Louisiana; and, the death of "Rebecca" due to heart disease.
There is an interesting letter, January 22, 1877, from S. O. Harris, Royal Oak, Talbot County, Maryland, to Caroline Davis, concerning an extract from Godey's Lady Book on the schooling of children and giving a discourse on female education. The correspondent writes that "the education of men and women should have some reference to their intellectual organization and capacities..."; advises "a harmonious development of the moral, physical and intellectual being" as the kind of education required for women; warns against "overtasking the youthful intellect of American girls"; asks that his motive not be taken unkindly; and, praises the course of study at the Southern Female College.
On August 6, 1879, "Carrie" Davis, Southern Female College, writes to her mother, Caroline Davis, mentioning attending protracted meetings, news of "Kittie" and George Drew, and life at Southern Female College. On August 25, 1880, Williams Thomas Davis writes his wife, "Carrie" [Caroline Virginia (Robinson) Davis], about the activities of the family; hearing excellent sermons by [John Cowper] Granberry (1829- 1907) at Market Street Church; and, imploring her to use her influence to find some students for their school. On August 28, 1880, Davis writes his children in Brunswick County an interesting letter giving his opinions on "the system of labor and arrangements of society," "masters & servants," and the mental energy of white people in contrast to the physical energy of "colored" people. He also advises them on how to be useful and happy and encourages the love of family and God. A touching letter, July 15, 1886, from Alice Clark expresses sympathy over the death of young "Carrie" Davis, empathizes with the loss of a loved one, expresses her own sorrow over losing her husband Emery, and gives religious encouragement. There is also a letter, February 8, 1904, from Robert Good Southall (1852-1924), House of Representatives, sending a copy of the Lincoln, Garfield and McKinley, eulogies. There is a carte-de-visite of Williams Thomas Davis as a mature gentleman.
Papers of the Davis family pertain to financial matters during 1854-1857. There is a letter, February 5, 1860, concerning the hire of one of the best overseers in Warren and discussing his character, work skills, and recent endeavors and advising the recipient on how to treat him. An August 6 letter, from James A. Davis in Pilgrim's Rest concerns a trip near Petersburg to Suffolk and Norfolk. A copy of a 1912 letter pertains to Seacrist Gold Mining Company, Petersburg, and contains a report of an examination of the property.
Papers of the Robinson family include letters, January 13 and March 28, 1852, from John B. Robinson, "Lebanon," Norfolk, to Mrs. [Ann] Clark Robinson, Brunswick County, concerning studying and wearing the uniform at the academy; being examined in February by many of the citizens of Norfolk; news of the marriage of Nelly Moseley; the suicide during a state of intoxication of David Kyle; snow killing many peaches, apricots, strawberries and other fruits; a young African-American being burnt by drinking hot grease and being treated by linseed oil; Aunt Martha having land cleared; and, his sisters Rowena, Lucy and Caroline. He comments on suicide, saying "these worldly minded men have nothing to support them in times of trouble give way to despair and plunge into eternal ruin." There are also two letters, January 6 and June 3, 1877, from Allen Y. and John B. Robinson in Orcus Island, Washington, stating their reasons for staying in such an outlandish country as the healthiness of the country and waiting to secure titles to their claims and the funds to pay for them. They write that they are providing assistance to needy families and selling eggs. They reveal that their plans to return to Virginia in 1862 were thwarted by the Civil War, and that they instead went to Caribou, British Columbia and built a large brick building in Victoria, British Columbia, which has deteriorated in value. They state that in 1864 they started trading on Puget Sound, Washington and afterwards took up two government land claims on Orcas Island. They admit that they cannot return to Virginia until receiving the title from the United States Government. The marriage of [Caroline Virginia (Robinson)] to [Williams Thomas] Davis is also mentioned.
Papers of William A. Shepard and Martha (Davis) Shepard include four letters. On August 5, 1866, there is a letter from Millville, Brunswick County, about a quarterly meeting conducted in Lawrenceville; personal and family news; travel plans and other activities; the damage caused by a thunderstorm; the meager wheat crops, splendid oat crops, and promising corn and tobacco crops; the difficulties in sending the daughters of local families back to school; and, news of the Price family and the Ashton Lewises. Letters of September 1866 mention travel in Virginia, interviewing a scholar, the visiting Davis children in Pilgrim's Rest, and Riddick having 130 pupils with daily arrivals, and request that catalogues be sent. An October 8, [1889] letter reveals that they helped fix up a little church in the country and attended a dedication with Dr. Kern and mentions "Charlie," a bright young man and good football player.
Papers relating to Educational Associations include: program for the Conference for Education in the South (1903); program for the Department of Public Instruction (1906); Constitution of the Virginia Association of Colleges and Schools for Girls (1906); program for the first annual meeting of VACSG (1907); Interstate Teachers' Agency (1907-1909); Department of Public Instruction circular concerning certification of teachers (1910); circular letter re the Educational Association of Virginia meeting, inviting teachers of Latin or Greek to join (1911); Nathaniel C. Starke, principal of Petersburg Military Academy (1911) enclosing circular; pamphlet, "Education in Virginia..." (1912) by Arthur Kyle Davis; and, pamphlet, "The Southern Seminary" (n.d.).
Business papers of the Petersburg Female College consist chiefly of receipts, ca. 1860-1863, for teachers' salaries. There are also bills for advertising, music and tuning the college's pianos.
Papers relating to Southern College (Junior) include a brochure, "Commencement Snap-Shots" depicting members of the graduating class (1934); program of finals (June 1936); letter, December 21, 1937, from Raleigh C. Powell Building Construction concerning an inspection of the Southern College buildings and property and replacement estimates; and, a "Book of Views" containing photographs of the college buildings and student groups and activities.
Business papers of the Southern Female College include accounts for advertising (1910-1913); a building addition to Davis' house at the college (January 1872); medical care (January 1872); clothing and food (1872); tuning pianos (June 1872); ink and composition books (July 1872); children's oak chairs (January 1873); and, a list of furniture and other items in the dining room and other rooms. There are catalogues and printed material of the Southern Female College, including a broadside (September 1879), catalogues (1887-1888 and 1892-1893), and a program of a Christmas concert (1913). Among the correspondence for the Southern Female College are a letter, September 2, 1905, from Marie Crosby concerning a position of teacher of music, and including testimonies; and, a letter, May 27, 1908, containing recommendations for Isabel K. Emerson. Insurance papers include an inspection and survey report of the buildings of the Southern Female College (December 1935).
Contents List
- Arthur Kyle Davis 1905-1929 (Box 1)
- Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. 1913-1932 (Box 1)
- William Thomas Davis and Caroline Virginia (Robinson) Davis 1866-1907 (Box 1)
- Davis Family 1854-1927 (Box 1)
- John B. Robinson 1852, 1877 (Box 1)
- William A. Shepard and Martha (Davis) Shepard 1866, 1889 (Box 1)
- Educational Associations 1903-1912 (Box 1)
- Petersburg Femal College: Business Papers 1860-1863, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Southern College (Junior) 1934-1937 (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Advertisements 1910-1913 (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Business Papers 1871-1873, n.d., 3 folders (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Catalogues and Printed 1879-1893, 1913 (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Correspondence 1905-1914 (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Insurance 1910, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Photographs n.d. (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Requests for Catalogues 1905-1914 (Box 1)
- Southern Female College: Telegrams 1898-1913 (Box 1)